Guide to the Algernon Swinburne Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Algernon Swinburne collection
1854-1908
GEN MSS 303
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.34
(8 boxes)
The collection consists of letters and manuscripts by Swinburne, including letters to Robert Browning; Andrew Chatto; John Camden Hotten; Joseph Knight; Thomas Purnell; Dante Gabriel, William Michael, and Christina Rossetti; William Bell Scott; Richard Herne Shepherd, and Theodore Watts-Dunton. Manuscripts of Swinburne's writings include working drafts of poems, the Chorus from Atalanta in Calydon, an early draft of Hymn to Proserpine, proofs of Channel Passage, and manuscripts of several prose works.
Total Boxes: ongoing
Swinburne, Algernon Charles, 1837-1909
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Source information is recorded on the folders. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to Algernon Swinburne, which the library has chosen to group and list as an artificial collection.
English poetry -- 19th century; Browning, Robert, 1812-1889; Chatto, Andrew, 1841-1913; Hotten, John Camden, 1832-1873; Knight, Joseph, 1829-1907; Purnell, Thomas, 1834-1889; Rossetti, Christina Georgina, 1830-1894; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; Rossetti, William Michael, 1829-1919; Scott, William Bell, 1811-1890; Shepherd, Richard Herne, 1842-1895; Swinburne, Algernon Charles, 1837-1909; Watts-Dunton, Theodore, 1832-1914; Chatto & Windus (Firm)
- Correspondence, Series I
  - LETTERS BY SWINBURNE
    - Autographed postcard signed to Arthur E. Aarons, [1903 Oct?] (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Purchase, 1950
    - ALS to Patrick Proctor Alexander, London, 1881 Aug 5 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Purchase, 1954
    - ALS to [Thomas Allsop], [London] (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Purchase, 1966
    - ALS to Richard Bagot, London, 1901 Mar 20 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 2 ALS to Thomas Spencer Baynes, Henley on Thames, Oxford; The Pines, Putney Hill, London, 1876, 1882 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Purchase, 1953
    - ALS to [Thomas Spencer Baynes?], London, 1883 Apr 7 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Purchase
    - ALS to William Black, The Pines, Putney Hill, London, 1888 Dec 12 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 8 ALS to Henry A. Bright, 1874-83 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Gift, 1950
    - ALS to Robert Browning, London, 1875 Feb 25 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - ALS to Robert Browning, [London], 1881 Jan 26 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Purchase, 1951
    - 86 ALS and 2 letters and a receipt signed, to Andrew Chatto of Chatto and Windus, 1874-1903 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
    - ALS to Andrew Chatto, The Pines, Putney Hill, [1882 Dec 26?] (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Gift, 1972
    - 2 ALS to Andrew Chatto, London, 1882; 1885 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Purchase, 1956; 1960
    - ALS to James Sutherland Cotton, [ca. 1892 Dec] (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Purchase, 1959
    - ALS to the editor of the Academy [James Sutherland Cotton?], 1892 Dec 28 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - ALS in French to Mme. [Tola] Dorian, London, [ca. 1882 Nov] (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Accompanied by typescript
    - APCS to Percy Dryden-Mundy, London, 1901 Jan 14 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Gift, 1968
    - ALS to James Nicol Dunn, London, 1899 Feb 20 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - ALS to Havelock Ellis, London, 1886 Nov 4 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - ALS (in French) to [Félix Fénéon?], London, 1884 May 8 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Purchase, 1956
    - ALS to Mr. Fletcher, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - 5 ALS to Frederick James Furnivall, London; Holmwood, Surrey, 1866-76 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - ALS to Richard Garnett, Alton, England, 1892 Aug 12 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - ALS to Edmund Gosse, London, 1893 Mar 24 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - ALS to Sabine Matilda Greville, The Pines, Putney, 1881 Feb 4 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Sends her the poem (printed in 1881
      under the title "Euthanatos") he had
      written on her mother's, Maria
      Thellusson, death; accompanied by a
      lock of Swinburne's hair
      Purchase, 1969
    - ALS to Alexander Ballock Grosart, London, 1896 Sep 19 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - ALS to Mrs. Thomas Gordon Hake, Holmwood, Henley on Thames, [1876] Jun 17 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      Purchase, 1958
    - ALS to John Camden Hotten, [1866] Nov 3 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - ALS to John Camden Hotten, Holmwood, Surrey, 1867 Jan 2 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - ALS to [John Camden Hotten], [1868 Jul?] (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - ALS to J.C. Hotten, Holmwood, [1872] Dec 2 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - ALS to [Charles Augustus] Howell, [Holmwood, Surrey], [1872] Aug 2 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - ALS to Messrs. J.W. Jarvis and Son, London, 1885 Oct 23 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - ALS to Margaret Jones, London, 1883 Dec 13 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      Accompanied with typescript
    - ALS to Mr. Knight, [London], [1866] Feb 4 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      Gift, 1943
    - 2 ALS to Joseph Knight, London, [1865,1874] (Box 1, Folder 37)
      Purchase, 1954; 1959
    - 4 ALS to Joseph Knight, 1865-66 (Box 1, Folder 38)
      Purchase, 1980
    - ALS to Joseph Knight, London, [1866?] Aug 3 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      Purchase, 1957
    - 2 ALS to James Thomas Knowles, London, 1884 May, Jun (Box 1, Folder 40)
      Purchase 1959
    - AL (fragment) to the editor of The Athenaeum [Norman MacColl], London, [1875] Jun 6 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - ALS to Philip [Bourke Marston], London, 1886 Nov 15 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - TLS to George Meredith, [1908 Feb] (Box 1, Folder 43)
      Also signed by Theodore Watts-Dunton
      Gift, 1960
    - ALS to Herman Charles Merivale, London, [1881 Sep] (Box 1, Folder 44)
      Purchase, 1960
    - 2 ALS and 1 AL (incomplete) to Mary Louisa Molesworth, London, 1884-96 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - ALS to William Morris, The Pines, Putney Hill, S.W., 1894 Jan 23 (Box 1, Folder 46)
      Note attributed to Sydney Cockerell
      on third page of sheet
      Purchase, 1972
    - 3 ALS to John Nichol, Capheaton, London, [1857]-84 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      Purchase, 1954; 1958
    - ALS to Reverend John Oliver, Bradford- on-Avon, Wilts, 1887 Aug 3 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      Pasted on letter is a small
      photograph of Swinburne
    - 20 ALS to Thomas Purnell, 1865-1877 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - ALS to Christina Rossetti, London, 1883 Jun 7 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - 2 ALS to Dante Gabriel Rossetti, London, [1870?], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 51)
      Purchase, 1961
    - 5 ALS to Lucy Brown Rossetti, London, 1884-92 (Box 1, Folder 52)
      Gift, 1960; 1962
    - ALS to William Michael Rossetti, The Pines, 1885 Jan 1 (Box 1, Folder 53)
      Gift, 1977
    - ALS to William Michael Rossetti, The Pines, 1891 Mar 22 (Box 1, Folder 54)
      Gift, 1973
    - ALS to William Michael Rossetti, The Pines, 1891 Nov 23 (Box 1, Folder 55)
      Compares the poetry of Victor Hugo to
      that of William Blake
      Gift, 1974
    - ALS in French, to [Comte Paul Jaques Raymond Binesse de Saint-Victor], Henley on Thames, 1872 Sep 19 (Box 2, Folder 56)
      Purchase, 1944
    - ALS to the Editor of the St. James's Gazette, 1889 Feb 28 (Box 2, Folder 57)
      Accompanied by a leaf torn from The
      Nineteenth Century, No. CCXLI, March
      1897, with 6 lines of manuscript
      verse added to his printed poem "For
      Greece and Crete".
    - 2 ALS to Frederick Sandys, London, 1874, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 58)
      Purchase, 1956; Gift, 1969
    - 16 ALS to [William Bell] Scott1859-82 (Box 2, Folder 59)
      Purchase, 1952
    - 11 ALS to Richard Herne Shepherd, Isle of Wight; London, [1874] (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - ALS to Mrs. Clement Shorter, The Pines, 1902 Apr ll (Box 2, Folder 61)
      Printed in and removed from his
      Letters on William Morris, Omar
      Khayyam and other subjects of
      interest, London 1910
    - ALS to Clement Shorter, The Pines, 1908 Sep 28 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - ALS to [Messrs. Smith, Elder & Co.], London, 1889 Dec 29 (Box 2, Folder 63)
      Purchase, 1964
    - ALS to editor of the Westminster Gazette [J. Alfred Spender], 1902 Jul 21 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - 3 ALS to [Marion Harry] Spielmann, London; Broxhead Warren, Alton, Hants, [1888]; 1892 (Box 2, Folder 65)
      Accompanied by 2 TLS from the
      librarian of the Chelsea Public
      Library and 3 TLS from the librarian
      of the Westminster Public Libraries
      to Percy E. Spielmann
      Purchase, 1965
    - ALS to Caroline Stansfield, London, [1870] Oct 1 (Box 2, Folder 66)
      Accompanied by a clipping about
      Giuseppe Mazzini
    - 2 ALS to Charles Henry Swinburne, Lower Easton; London, 1854; [1861] (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - 3 ALS to Isabel Swinburne, London, [1880;88]; 190 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - ALS to Arthur Symons, London, 1908 May 13 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - ALS to [Frank D. Thomas], 1884 Dec 21 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - ALS to Henry Wallis, London, [1865] (Box 2, Folder 71)
      The paper is watermarked "1865"
      Purchase, 1975
    - 55 ALS and 3 autograph signed postcards to Theodore Watts-Dunton, [1872-96?] (Box 2, Folder 71a-73)
    - 30 ALS to Walter Theodore Watts-Dunton, 1872-96 (Box 2, Folder 74)
      Accompanied by two pictures of
      Swinburne and Watts-Dunton and
      illuminated title-page
    - 3 ALS to Francis Gledstanes Waugh, London; Holmwood, Shiplake, Henley on Thames, 1868-73 (Box 2, Folder 75)
      Purchase, 1958; 1959
    - ALS to Stephen Wheeler, London, 1899 Jan 29 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - ALS to Stephen Wheeler, London, 1907 May 5 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - ALS to Stephen Wheeler, London, 1908 Dec ll (Box 2, Folder 78)
      Purchase, 1934
    - ALS to unidentified recipient, concerning his essay on William Blake, [London], [1864] Feb 22 (Box 2, Folder 79)
      Gift, 1951
    - ALS to unidentified recipient, London, [1877] Oct 24 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - ALS to unidentified recipient, [London], 1880 Nov 3 (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - ALS to unidentified recipient, The Pines, Putney Hill, London, 1889 Jul 21 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - ALS to unidentified recipient, London, 1890 Apr 16 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - AL draft to an unidentified recipient, The Pines, 1890 Oct 30 (Box 2, Folder 84)
      Page 4 begins the draft of a poem,
      "It might prevent starvation.. ."
      Gift, 1975
    - ALS to unidentified recipient, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - ALS to an unidentified recipient, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - LETTERS TO AND ABOUT SWINBURNE
    - Clayden, Peter William. TL to Algernon Charles Swinburne, London, 1899 Aug 8 (Box 2, Folder 87)
      With Swinburne's reply written in
      ink across the top
      Gift, 1969
    - Trevelyan, Pauline Jermyn. ALS to [William Bell] Scott, mentioning Swinburne, Newcastle on Tyne, 1860 May (Box 2, Folder 88)
- Writings, Series II
  - POEMS
    - Astrea Victrix: autograph manuscript poem of 10 stanzas, with corrections and additions (Box 3, Folder 89)
      Gift, 1952
    - Atalanta in Calydon: Chorus, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 90)
      Poem, AMs, with many changes in same
      hand
    - A Ballad of Life, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 91)
      Early holograph draft
    - Prologue to "The Broken Heart:" autograph manuscript poem with the printed version from "A Channel Passage" and other poems, London, 1904 (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - "Carol for Charity:" manuscript, 1905 Nov 24 (Box 3, Folder 93)
      Purchase, 1989
    - "Channel Passage" (proof sheets), 1904 (Box 3, Folder 94-95)
      Gift, 1956
    - Hymn to Proserpine: autograph manuscript, initialed, with 52 lines of an early draft, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 96)
      Purchase, 1947
    - "In Memory of Barry Cornwall", AMs, 1874 Oct 14 (Box 3, Folder 97)
    - "A Jacobite's Farewell, 1715" AMs, 1888-92 (Box 3, Folder 98)
    - Holograph draft of "A Leave Taking", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 99)
    - "O little song," manuscript poem, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 100)
    - "Olive," in the English Illustrated Magazine, 1888 Oct (Box 3, Folder 101)
      Accompanied by AMs correction in
      stanzas vi-vii
    - Holograph manuscript draft "Song" from "The Sisters", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 102)
    - Prologue to "A Very Woman," AMs poem with printed version, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 103)
    - "What is death?" AMS poem, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 104)
      Accompanied by "No sweeter thing than
      children's ways and wills"
  - PROSE
    - "Ce Qui Peut se Passer Dans un Cab Safety:" autograph manuscript story, 1860-61
      Apparently a fragment of a chapter
      of "La Fille du Policeman"
      Gift, 1967
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Volume 4, folder 116
    - "Charles Reade:" autograph manuscript signed with corrections and addition in the author's hand (Box 3, Folder 105)
    - "Dedicatory Epistle:" holograph manuscript dedicatory epistle to the first collected edition of his Poems, London, 1904 (Box 3, Folder 106)
    - Typed copy, dedicatory epistle of the first collected edition of his poems, [1904] (Box 3, Folder 107)
    - Mr. Whistler's Lecture on Art: facsimile of the autograph manuscript, signed, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 108)
      This facsimile was issued with the
      following note: 'This essay is said
      to have caused the estrangement
      between Whistler and Swinburne, which
      continued until Whistler's death'
      Purchase, 1946
    - The Work of Robert Browning: autograph manuscript essay [incomplete], n.d. (Box 3, Folder 109)
      Accompanied by a manuscript note in
      the hand of Thomas J. Wise
    - Holograph Manuscript: "Comment on Lockhart's Life of Scott", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 110)
    - Holograph manuscript: "Notes on Herodotus", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 111)
    - List of Titles of Poems headed "Selections" with revisions on a sheet of blue paper, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 112)
      Also part of an Essay with references
      to Marlowe, Keats and Shelley, on a
      half sheet of paper and other
      manuscript material
- Philip M. Neufeld Swinburne Material, [1868-87]; Series III
  - English Poems: manuscript, working drafts, some revisions, [1868-87]
    Includes fragment (1L.) of early
    version of [Atlanta in Calydon]
    Purchase, 1995
    See: Volume 5, folder 117
  - Literary manuscripts, n.d.
    Includes [William Collins]:
    manuscript; "Short Notes on English
    Poets:" manuscript; an untitled and
    incomplete work on poetry:
    manuscript; "On Dramatic Poetry:"
    manuscript; [Le Cenci:] manuscript
    See: Volume 6, folder 118
  - "Philip Massinger, An Essay:" manuscript with correction and revisions
    See: Volume 7, folder 119
  - St. Dorothy: poem manuscript with revisions and emendations (Box 3, Folder 113)
  - "Trafalgar Day:" poem manuscript, 1895 Oct 21 (Box 3, Folder 114)
  - Theophile de [Viau]
    - Manuscript with deletions and emendations, [London], [1862?] (Box 3, Folder 115)
    - Portfolio, with bookplates of Jerome Kern and John Stuart Groves (Box 3, Folder 115a)
      Purchase 1995
- Oversize, [1860-61]
  - "Ce Qui Peut se Passer Dans un Cab- Safety": autograph manuscript story, [1860-61] (Box 4, Folder 116)
  - English Poems: manuscript, working drafts, some revisions, [1868-87] (Box 5, Folder 117)
  - Literary manuscripts, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 118)
  - "Philip Massinger, An Essay:" manuscript with correction and revisions (Box 7, Folder 119)
- Additions Since August 1999, n.d.; Series IV
  - Manuscript of "The Garden of Proserpine" in an unidentified hand (Box 8, Folder 120)
    Sheets marked with page numbers in
    printer's red pencil.
    Acc: 20010131-c
  - ALS to [Alfred Ainger?]; The Pines, Putney Hill, S.W., 1886 Feb 25 (Box 8, Folder 121)
    Concerning Swinburne's collection
    of Charles Lamb materials.
    Acc: 20030205-m